Finding Aid for G.M. (Gerard M.) Faeth papers, 1964-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
G.M. (Gerard M.) Faeth papers 1964-2005, 1985-2005
Faeth, G. M. (Gerard M.)
12 linear feet (in 13 boxes)
0726 Aa 2
Gerard Faeth (1936-2005) professor of aerospace engineering and mechanical engineering was a world-renowned scholar, researcher, and NASA advisor on theoretical and experimental research on combustion, heat transfer, fluid dynamics, and instrumentation. The collection includes correspondence, teaching materials, research proposals, presentations and publications, photographs and other visual materials reflecting his academic, research, and consulting career. The collection covers the years 1964-2005, but primarily documents 1985-2005.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers (donor no. 9591 ) were received from Mary Ann Faeth on April 22, 2005.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Gerard Michael Faeth was born in New York City on July 5, 1936. He was the son of Joseph Faeth and Helen Wagner.1 He started undergraduate coursework in mechanical engineering at Union College in Schenectady, New York, and was a recipient of the Frank Bailey Scholarship. In 1958 he received his Bachelor's of Mechanical Engineering (BME).2 Upon graduation Faeth accepted a graduate assistantship at Pennsylvania State University (PSU) to study mechanical engineering. He joined A. W. Hussman's diesel laboratory, where he learned fundamentals of experimental research.3 Upon completion of his Master's in 1961, Faeth pursued his Ph.D., and in 1964 he was awarded his Ph.D. in Mechanical Engineering. In 1964, Faeth was offered and accepted a joint appointment with the department of mechanical engineering and the Applied Research Laboratory (formerly the Ordnance Research Laboratory) at PSU [1], where he worked from 1964-1985.
Though his research primarily drew from mechanical engineering, Faeth's research stretched across many disciplines, such as physics and chemistry. Faeth distinguished himself as a high caliber researcher and scholar in the area of "combustion science, heat transfer, propulsion systems, and fluid dynamics with a particular emphasis on the properties of evaporating and combustion sprays, explosions and unwanted fires." [1]. He conducted his work as both researcher and consultant within a variety of organizations and corporations. Most notably, was his work for the Applied Research Laboratory where he researched the development of underwater power and propulsion systems. On October 1, 1974, Faeth was granted a patent for the United States Navy for the development of a steady heat generating reactor. In 1977, Faeth was a consultant for the Union Carbide Corporation studying the exothermic decomposition of liquids and a researcher at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Lewis Research Center examining aircraft emissions (1978) and combustion fundamentals (1984). He also consulted for General Motors Corporation Research Laboratories, researching internal combustion engines.
In 1979 he was awarded the Outstanding Achievement in Research Award from the College of Engineering at PSU. Faeth served as a member of the Editorial Advisory Board of Combustion Science and Technology from 1977-2002 and was a member of the Editorial Board for Combustion and Flame from 1978-1983.
Between the years of 1975 and 1985, Faeth was not only a professor of mechanical engineering at PSU, he was also the acting head for the department in 1983.4 At PSU and the University of Michigan, Faeth "taught courses in Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering at both the undergraduate and graduate level." He also directed "thirty-two post-doctoral Research Fellows, and fifty-three doctoral students in Aerospace and Mechanical Engineering, as well a Fulbright Fellow." For his excellence in teaching Faeth was given the distinction of Professor Emeritus of Mechanical Engineering at PSU in 1985, and in 1990 was honored with an Outstanding Alumnus Award. [3]
In July 1985, Faeth joined the University of Michigan as an associate research scientist and professor. Soon after he became the Arthur B. Modine Professor of Aerospace Engineering and the Head of the Gas Dynamics Laboratories, where he specialized in combustion, heat transfer, and fluid dynamics.5 Three years following this appointment, Faeth became a Fellow of the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics, he won the Heat Transfer Memorial Award from the American Society of Mechanical Engineering, and the Excellence in Research Award from the College of Engineering. [3]
In 1989, "Faeth began studying the structure of soot and the conditions under which it is produced, with the aim of finding ways to control soot during the combustion process."6 His work focused on the "Laminar Soot Processes (LSP) Experiment, which flew as part of the NASA Microgravity Science Laboratory (MSL) Mission in 1997."[5] The data collected from the nearly 21 experiments conducted on that mission provided a strong base for subsequent experiments focused on laminar soot processes and had many practical applications such as the prevention of flame spread during the combustion process in engines, and the development of cleaner automobile and jet engines. He also researched microgravity conditions in spacecraft environments by conducting several experiments aboard the Space Shuttle Columbia (Flights STS-83, 94, and 107) as well as the International Space Station (ISS). Tragically, Faeth lost several of his student colleagues when the Space Shuttle Columbia disintegrated upon re-entry in 2003.7 In 1993, Faeth was again recognized for his excellence in research by the University of Michigan. In 1992 he received the Distinguished Engineering Faculty Research Award and in 1993 he was recognized with the Stephen S. Atwood Award, which is the highest award given to faculty of the engineering college.[3]
Throughout his academic, research, and consulting career, Faeth was very active in several professional associations. He sat on the board of directors of the Combustion Institute for nine years (1988-1997) and chaired several of its committees, he was an active and member and chaired several committees in the Heat Transfer Division of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. Most prominently, he was an active member and advisor for NASA, chairing the Microgravity Research Advisory Committee and the Life and Microgravity Sciences and Applications Advisory Committee from 1997-1999. He was also the Vice-Chair for the Biological and Physical Research Advisory Committee from 2001-2005, as well as member (1998-2001) and Chair (1993-1997) of the Microgravity Combustion Science Discipline Working Group. Faeth was well-known for his role on the NASA Advisory Council where he served from 1997-1999. [3]
Faeth wrote over 500 articles and gave numerous presentations and talks, especially as an advisor for the United States Government. Some of his most critical publications center around the work he did with laminar flames and soot. Of particular note are Structure of Round, Fully Developed, Buoyant Turbulent Plumes and Turbulence Generation by Drops in Dense Sprays.
In 2005, Faeth was awarded a distinguished university professorship for his excellence in teaching and research; the highest honor the University of Michigan can bestow upon a faculty member. On January 24, 2005, Gerard Faeth died in his Ann Arbor home. The Department of Aerospace Engineering at the University of Michigan established the Gerard Faeth Memorial Fund to remember him and his many contributions to aerospace engineering and sponsors an annual memorial lecture."8 He was survived by his wife Mary Ann Faeth and three daughters- Christine Louise, Lorraine Vera, and Elinor Jean.
____________________________________
Notes:
1. Marquis Who's Who on the Web
2. ASME Fellow News Release, 2/29/1980, Folder 4 in Biographical Series.
3. History of Mechanical Engineering, Chapter 6, Pennsylvania State University Website- http://www.mne.psu.eduHistory/ch6.html
4. Gerard Faeth's Resume, Folder 8 in Biographical Series
5 "Distinguished professor dies," Michigan Daily, January 27, 2005.
6."Laminar Soot Processes: Gerard Faeth's Biography" Microgravity News, Spring 2000, NASA Marshall Flight Center in conjunction with Hampton University or http://microgravity.grc.nasa.gov/combustion/lsp/lsp_faeth.htm
7. Obituaries-Gerard Faeth The University Record Online, January 31, 2005, http://www.umich.edu/~urecord/0405/Jan31_05/obits.shtml
8."The G. M. Faeth Memorial Fund", The Combustion Institute, http://www.combustioninstitute.org/documents/TheGMFaethMemorialFund.pdf
The Gerard Faeth papers include correspondence, teaching materials, research proposals, presentations and publications, photographs, and other visual materials documenting his career. The Faeth papers (approx. 12 linear feet) date from 1964-2005, but primarily document the period 1985-2005. The papers are organized into six series: Biographical; Teaching and Academic Activities; Professional Activities; Research; Presentations, Publications, and Reviews; and Visual Materials.
Subjects:
Aircraft exhaust emissions.; Combustion--Research.; Faeth, G. M. (Gerard M.); Heat transmission.; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Aerospace Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Mechanical Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
DVDs.; Videotapes.
- Biographical 1976-2004
  Biographical, 1976-2004 (0.5 linear feet) is an alphabetically arranged topical sequence containing awards and honors, interviews, biographical sketches and resumes of Gerard Faeth. Included in this series are drafts of Faeth's undelivered speech written for the Distinguished University Professor Award.
  - Awards and Honors 1980-2004 (Box 1)
    - APS Fellowship 2003 (Box 1)
    - Distinguished University Professor Award 2004 (Box 1)
    - Sir Alfred C. Edgerton Gold Medal 2004 (Box 1)
    - Various 1980-1989, 2004 (Box 1)
  - BEST-Michigan Profile 1986-1996, undated (Box 1)
  - Biographical Sketches 2001-2004, undated (Box 1)
  - HighlyCited Files, (ISI) 2001 (Box 1)
  - Interviews 1985-1986 (Box 1)
  - Resumes 1993, 2003-2005, undated (Box 1)
  - Who's Who, 1976-2004 (Box 1)
- Teaching and Academic Activities 1964-2005
  Teaching and Academic Activities, 1964-2005 (bulk dates from 1980-2005), (1 linear foot) is an alphabetically arranged topical sequence documenting Gerard Faeth's involvement at the University of Michigan in the departments of Aerospace and Mechanical Engineering as professor and researcher. It is divided into two sub-series: General, and Classes. General primarily includes correspondence, faculty activity plans and reports, sabbatical files, and consulting agreements. Classes includes teaching and course materials for Aerospace Engineering 225, 320, 533, and 585. Also included are materials reflecting his involvement in a variety of university committees, such as the Building Committee for the new Aerospace Engineering Laboratory and the Chair Search Advisory Committee for the Aerospace and Mechanical Engineering departments.
  - General 1964-2004
    - Adjunct Professorship at King Fahd University of Petroleum and Minerals 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - Application for Joint Appointment to Mechanical Engineering 2003 (Box 1)
    - Consulting Reports 1987, 1991-2004 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 2001, 2003-2004 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Activity Plans 1998-2004 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Activity Reports 1964-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Gas Dynamics Laboratories 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Student Research Assistants and Post-Doctoral Appointments 1992-2004 (Box 1)
    - Sabbatical Files 2002 (Box 1)
  - Classes 1985-2005
    - Aerospace Engineering 225 (Introduction to Gas Dynamics)
      - Faculty Course Survey, fall 2004 (Box 1)
    - Aerospace Engineering 320 (Introduction to Gas Dynamic I)
      - Draft Syllabus 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Aerospace Engineering 533 (Combustion Processes)
      - Course Outline, fall 1985 (Box 1)
      - Course Pack, winter 2003, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Lectures 1-29, winter 2005, 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Faculty Course Survey, winter 2004 (Box 1)
    - Aerospace Engineering 585 (Aerospace Engineering Seminar)
      - Draft Syllabus and Background Information, winter 2005 (Box 1)
      - Seminar Schedules 2002-2005 (Box 1)
      - Faculty Course Surveys, fall 2003 and winter 2004 (Box 1)
  - Committees 1985-2005
    - Accreditation Board for Engineering and Technology 1987-1993 (Box 2)
    - Building Committee 1985-1993, undated
      - Correspondence 1985-1993, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - Drawings/Designs undated (Box 2)
      - Lab Allocations 1988 undated (Box 2)
    - Chair Search Advisory Committees 2003-2004, undated
      - Aerospace Engineering
        - Announcements/Correspondence (Box 2)
        - Campus Interviews (Box 2)
        - Form Letters (Box 2)
        - Nomination Lists (Box 2)
        - Reports (Box 2)
        - Roster (Box 2)
      - Mechanical Engineering
        - Announcement (Box 2)
    - College of Engineering Endowed Chair Advisory Committee 2003 (Box 2)
    - College of Engineering Internal Review 2004-2005 (Box 2)
    - College of Engineering Review Committee
      - Promotion/Tenure Casebook Example 1991 (Box 2)
    - Engineering Research Center Pre-proposal Evaluations 2004 (Box 2)
    - Space Allocation 1997-2005 (Box 2)
    - Wind Tunnel Construction 1993 (Box 2)
- Professional Activities 1991-2005
  Professional Activities, 1991-2005 (approx. 0.5 linear feet) is an alphabetically arranged sequence of materials that documents Faeth's professional activity within scientific organizations and advisory committees, research related working groups, as well as his external consulting work. Of particular note is Faeth's involvement with the Life and Microgravity Sciences and Applications Advisory Committee (NASA),where he served as chair from 1997-1999 and vice-chair from 1999-2001, and the Microgravity Science and Applications Science Council (Universities Space Research Association), where he was a member from 1999-2005.
  - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics (AIAA) Technical Committee 1997, 2000 (Box 2)
  - ASTM Fire Suppression Working Group 2003 (Box 2)
  - Aviation Environmental Design Tool Workshop Committee 2003-2005
    - Agendas and Minutes 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Copyright Agreement 2003 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 2003-2004 (Box 2)
    - Membership Lists undated (Box 2)
    - Reports 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - Biological and Physical Research Advisory Committee (BPRAC) 2004 (Box 2)
  - Canadian Space Agency Physical Science Review Program 2004 (Box 2)
  - Daniel Guggenheim Medal Board of Awards 2002-2005 (Box 2)
  - Life and Microgravity Sciences and Applications Advisory Committee (NASA) 1992-2004 (Box 2)
  - Microgravity Science and Applications Science Council (Universities Space Research Association) 1999, 2002-2004 (Box 2)
  - National Academies' Engineering, Applied Sciences and Mathematics Panel 2005 (Box 2)
  - National Academies' Jefferson Science Fellows Competition 2004-2005 (Box 2)
  - National Academy of Engineering 2001-2003 (Box 2)
  - National Research Council Associateship Awards 2004 (Box 2)
  - Office of Biological and Physical Research Free Flyer Research Roadmap Workshop 2003 (includes compact disc) (Box 2)
  - Pratt & Whitney Consulting 2002 (Box 2)
  - Space Science and Applications Advisory Committee 1991 (Box 2)
  - Virginia Tech Graduate Program Review Committee 2004-2005 (Box 2)
- Research 1983-2005
  Research, 1983-2005 (4.5 linear feet) is an alphabetically arranged sequence documenting the research career of Gerard Faeth. Research in this series is organized by the funding research institution or agency and is further divided into sub-series of experiments or research projects. Within each experiment or research project are relevant correspondence, proposals and supporting materials, progress reports, final reports, and financial records. Of particular note in this series is Faeth's ground-breaking research conducted while working under the auspices of NASA on microgravity combustion and Laminar Soot Processes (LSP), which flew as part of the Microgravity Science Laboratory Mission I in 1997. Also, of interest is his Soot Production in a Coflow Environment (SPICE) research conducted under NASA, in which Faeth studied non-buoyant round laminar jet diffusion flames.
  - Advisory Group for Aerospace Research and Development (AGARD) 1988-1996
    - Consultant Agreements 1988-1989, 1995 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence 1990, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Proposals and Reports 1990, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Air Force Office of Scientific Research (AFOSR) 1983-2005
    - General 1983-2003, undated
      - Assignment Agreement 1983 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1988-2003 (Box 2)
      - Report Documentations (various) 1989-1990, undated (Box 2)
      - Requisition Reports 1985, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Basic Research Program in Air-Breathing Combustion (Box 3)
      - Proposal 1984 (Box 3)
    - Breakup and Turbulence Generation in Dense Sprays
      - Financial Materials 1992-1993, 1995 (Box 3)
      - Progress Reports 1992-2002 (Box 3)
      - Project Award Changes 1993, 1995 (Box 3)
      - Proposal 1992 (Box 3)
    - Combined Cycle Propulsion, Multi-University Research Initiative (MURI)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 2003 (Box 3)
    - Dense-Spray Structure and Phenomena
      - Financial Materials 1985-1989 (Box 3)
      - Grant Amendments 1985-1989 (Box 3)
      - Progress Reports 1986-1987 (Box 3)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 1985, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Drop-Gas Interactions in Dense Sprays
      - Annual Reports 1990, 1999-2004 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence 1998-2004 (Box 3)
      - Final Reports 1988-1989 (Box 3)
      - Financial Materials 1985, 1988-1992, 1995, 1999-2003 (Box 3)
      - Monthly Progress Reports February 2002-November 2004 (Box 3)
      - Proposals 1989, 1998-2002, undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Ruby Laser Proposal Materials (Double-Pulsed Holography for Studies of Drop Dynamics and Breakup) 1992 (Box 3)
    - Liquid Breakup in Dense Sprays
      - Monthly Progress Reports January 2005 (Box 3)
      - Project Award Changes 2004 (Box 3)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 2004 (Box 3)
    - Secondary Breakup and Turbulence Interactions of Drops
      - Correspondence 1994-1997 (Box 3)
      - Progress Reports 1994-1998 (Box 3)
      - Project Award Changes 1995-1998 (Box 3)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 1994-1998 (Box 3)
    - Velocimetry for Studies of Turbulence Generation in Dense Sprays
      - Proposal Materials 1997 (Box 3)
  - Army Ballistic Research Laboratory 1992
    - Open-Loop Response of Combusting Liquid Monopropellant Sprays
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 1992 (Box 3)
  - Army Research Office 1985, 1986, 1989
    - Droplet Combustion of HAN-Based Monopropellants at High Pressures
      - Proposal 1989 (Box 3)
    - Liquid Propellant Combustion
      - Proposal 1985 (Box 3)
    - Structure of Monopropellant Spray Flames at Elevated Pressures
      - Proposal 1986 (Box 3)
  - General Electric (GE) Initiative 2004-2005
    - Fundamental Investigation of Round Liquid Jet Injection in Parallel and Cross Streams
      - Correspondence 2004 (Box 3)
      - Proposal 2005 (Box 3)
  - National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) 1990-2004
    - General
      - Correspondence 1999-2003 (Box 3)
      - Figures and Calculations undated (Box 3)
      - Publications (relevant) 1999, 2003 (Box 3)
    - Chemically-Passive Suppression of Premixed Flames in Spacecraft Environments at Microgravity
      - Progress Reports 2003-2004 (Box 4)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 2002-2004 (Box 4)
    - Chemically-Passive Suppression of Laminar Non-premixed (Diffusion) Flames
      - Proposal Materials 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - Diagnostics Development for a Flight Experiment on Soot Processes in Diffusion Flames
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Effects of Electrical Field on Soot Processes on Non-buoyant Hydrocarbon Flames
      - Consultant Contracts 2002-2003 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1999-2001 (Box 4)
      - Progress Reports undated (Box 4)
      - Proposal 2000 (Box 4)
    - Flow/ Soot-Formation in Non-buoyant Laminar Diffusion Flames
      - Annual Task book 2003-2004 (Box 4)
    - Flow/ Soot-Formation Interactions in Non-buoyant Laminar Diffusion Flames
      - Annual Reports 1999, 2001-2002 (Box 4)
      - Cumulative Quarterly Report January 1999-September 2002 (Box 4)
      - Monthly Progress Reports February 1999-December 2002 (Box 4)
      - Project Award Changes 1999-2002 (Box 4)
    - Flow/ Soot-Formation Interactions in Non-buoyant Laminar Diffusion Flames (cont.)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 1998 (Box 4)
    - Investigation of Laminar Jet Diffusion Flames in Microgravity: A Paradigm for Soot Processes in Turbulent Flames
      - Annual Task Book 1999-2004 (Box 4)
      - Project Award Changes 1991-1993 (Box 4)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 1990-1994 (Box 4)
    - Laminar Soot Processes Experiment (LSP)
      - Continuation of Research Proposals 1994-1997, 2000, 2002 (Box 4)
      - Correspondence 1992-1994, 1997-2003, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Cumulative Quarterly Reports October 1993-September 2002 (Box 4)
      - Final Year Research Report 2004 (Box 4)
      - Monthly Progress Reports June 1991-January 2005, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Press Materials and Publications 1993, 1997, 2000-2003 (Box 4)
      - Project Award Changes 1994-2004 (Box 4)
      - Proposals 1994, 1998, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Soot Temperature Measurement System Test Report 1995 (Box 5)
    - Properties of Aerated-Liquid Jets in Subsonic Crossflow
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 2001 (Box 5)
    - Smoke Point in Coflow Experiment (SPICE)
      - Correspondence 1996-2002 (Box 5)
      - Pictures and Formulas (includes 2 compact discs & photos) June 1999 (Box 5)
      - Proposal and Presentations (Glovebox) 1998-1999 (Box 5)
    - Soot Formation in Freely-Propagating Laminar Premixed Flames
      - Combustion Science Reviews undated (Box 5)
      - Project Award Changes 1997-2000 (Box 5)
      - Proposal Materials 1995-1996 (Box 5)
    - Structure of Non-buoyant Laminar Jet Diffusion Flames 2000
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 2000 (Box 5)
    - STS-83 and STS-94 Flame Data, includes photos undated, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - STS-107
      - Pre-flight Briefing 2002 (Box 5)
      - Post-flight Investigators Working Group Symposium 2004 (Box 5)
  - National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST-formerly National Bureau of Standards (NBS) 1975-2004
    - General
      - Correspondence 1989-2004 (Box 5)
    - Buoyant Turbulent Jets and Plumes in Crossflows
      - Correspondence 2002 (Box 5)
      - Monthly Progress Reports December 1998-November 2004 (Box 5)
      - Proposal and Supporting Materials 1998-2000, 2002, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Quarterly Technical Reports October 1998, December 2001 (Box 5)
    - Investigation of Fire Impingement on a Horizontal Ceiling
      - Proposals 1977-1981, undated (Box 5)
    - Investigation of Fire Induced Plumes Along a Vertical Wall
      - Proposals 1975-1976 (Box 5)
    - Investigation of Turbulent Fires on Vertical and Inclined Walls
      - Annual Reports 1983, 1985 (Box 5)
      - Proposals 1982-1984 (Box 5)
    - Mixing and Radiation Properties of Buoyant Luminous Flame Environments
      - Correspondence 1994-1996 (Box 5)
      - Monthly Progress Reports November 1994-May 2000 (Box 6)
      - Project Award Changes 1994-1997 (Box 6)
      - Proposals 1995-1996 (Box 6)